Guide to the Children's Colonies Photograph Collection ALBA.PHOTO.148
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Children's Colonies Photographs
1937-1938
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives
ALBA.PHOTO.148
0.5 Linear Feet
During the Spanish Civil War (1936-1939) Colonias Infantiles (children's colonies) were established in rural locales by the government of the Spanish Republic after fascist forces bombed Spanish cities, and many thousands of children were orphaned, driven from their homes or made destitute by war. Children's colonies were established in Spain, and individuals and groups of child refugees were also sent abroad for safety. Spanish children's colonies were founded in France and the United Kingdom at this time. The collection contains photographs of children eating, bathing, studying, doing chores, resting, and playing.
(1 box), 356 black and white photographs sized from 3 3/8 x 4 ½ inches to 9 ½ x 7 1/8 inches.
Provenance
The Children's Colonies Photograph Collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
During the Spanish Civil War (1936-1939), roughly 200,000 of the 600,000 refugees seeking shelter from the armies of Generalissimo Franco and his fascist allies were children. Many children were orphaned or lost their homes. The bombing of large cities placed children at greatest risk, and many were moved to safer locations in the rural periphery. The government of the Spanish Republic established colonias infantiles (children's colonies), often in rural estates which had been abandoned by fascist sympathizers. Some parents and guardians sent children, individually or in groups, abroad for safety. Children's colonies were established in Spain, as well as in France and the United Kingdom, affording young refugees the opportunity to receive an education, medical care, and the company of other Spanish children. Photographs of children in these homes or colonies were taken for use in periodicals or publicity material, either produced by the Republic or produced and distributed by aid organizations in various countries.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: The Children's Colonies Photograph Collection consists of photographs related to the children's colonies in Spain and France. A number of the prints are stamped to indicate that they were taken for the Propaganda Section of the Republic's Children's Aid organization (Ajut Infantil de Reraguarda). The collection contains photographs of children eating, bathing, studying, doing chores, resting, and playing. Some images show teachers or other adult staff of the colonies. A number of files include exterior views of colony buildings, and interior shots of dormitories and dining halls. Of the total, 347 black and white prints are in files arranged alphabetically by either the name or the location of the colony. In addition to the images of children in identified colonies, there are ten images of children with donated toys and nine images of children in undesignated locations.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic. The photographic prints are identified by four numbers separated by colons. The first number refers to the collection number, the second to the box number, the third to the folder number, and the fourth to the individual print. For example, the first print in this collection is labeled 148:1:1:1.
The files are grouped into one series:
Missing Title
I, Photographs
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Pictorial works; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Children; Black-and-white photographs.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.
- Series I: Photographs
  - Children's Colony: Agen, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Children's Colony: Alborache, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Children's Colony: Antonio Coll, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Children's Colony: Bayona, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Children's Colony: Benimamet, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Children's Colony: Bierres, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Children's Colony: Breviere, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Children's Colony: Brughés (Gara), ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Children's Colony: Buñol, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Children's Colony: Can Toni Gross, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Children's Colony: Castillo de Alpina, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Children's Colony: Cerbere, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Children's Colony: Chantilly, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Children's Colony: Clara Zetkin, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Children's Colony: Colonia de Ingleses (Puigcerda), ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Children's Colony: Cuart de Poblet, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Children's Colony: Denia, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Children's Colony: Els Pins, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Children's Colony: Ferrer y Guardia, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Children's Colony: Francesc Macia (Vallflorida), ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Children's Colony: La Garriga, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Children's Colony: Luis Companys, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Children's Colony: Macastre, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Children's Colony: Masarrochos, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Children's Colony: Olira, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Children's Colony: Pasionaria, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Children's Colony: Perello, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Children's Colony: Perpignan, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Children's Colony: Petite-Synthe, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Children's Colony: Picaña No. 1, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Children's Colony: Picaña No. 2, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Children's Colony: Picaña No. 3, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Children's Colony: Ribarroja, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Children's Colony: Rosa Luxemburgo, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Children's Colony: Saint-Hilaire, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Children's Colony: Sete, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Children's Colony: Sitjes, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Children's Colony: Sueca, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Children's Colony: Torriente, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Children's Colony: Valence, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Children's Colony: Villalgordo del Jucar, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Spanish Children, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Spanish Children: Gifts for Children, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 44)